<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Severall circircumstances [sic] to prove that Mris Jane Berkeley and Sr VVilliam Killigrew have combined together to defraud me of an estate left unto me by Henry Killigrew Esq; for payment of his debts, for which I lye now in prison.</title>
            <author>Lygon, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88668</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865973</idno>
  <idno type="VID">166866</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240941683</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3560</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E732_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206878</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865973</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865973e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88668)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166866)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 113:E732[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Severall circircumstances [sic] to prove that Mris Jane Berkeley and Sr VVilliam Killigrew have combined together to defraud me of an estate left unto me by Henry Killigrew Esq; for payment of his debts, for which I lye now in prison.</title>
                  <author>Lygon, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Rich: Lygon.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>"Circumstances concerning Mris Ayliffe, to prove this combination and fraud between Sr William Killigrew and Mris Jane Berkeley, in cheating me of an estate left unto me by Sr Henry Killigrew for payment of his debts, for which I now lye in prison." has caption title on p.17.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march 18. 1653".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Berkeley, Jane --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Killigrew, William, --  Sir, 1606-1695 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Killigrew, Henry, 1613-1700 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Estates (Law) --  England --  Cases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166866:1"/>
            <head>Severall Circircumstances to prove that M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
               <hi>Jane Berkeley</hi> and S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>William Killi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grew</hi> have combined together to defraud me of an estate left unto me by <hi>Henry Killigrew</hi> Esq; for payment of his debts, for which I lye now in prison.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd first, her envying and railing on the said M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Killigrew</hi> after his death, for his subtill and unfaithfull dealing with her, that having courted her for a long time with promising language, and given her strong hopes of leaving her sole mistres of his estate, should fall off, and leave her but a part. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he had cousened her of her portion, which he perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her to venture in the <hi>Fens,</hi> which was now lost by reason the <hi>Fens</hi> were destroyed: which language certainly she would not have used, if the whole estate had been conferred upon her; yet notwithstanding she possest her self of all his writings and evidences, and consequently of his estate. And having in her hands a Will made by the said M. <hi>Killigrew</hi> at <hi>Exeter,</hi> (and no doubt provok't unto it by her self, in the name her brother Sir <hi>John Berkeley</hi> was then Governour there, whose countenance might much further the business) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he gives her all or the greatest part of his estate. By virtue of which Will she makes sale of a great part of the estate, though she never proved the Will: And finding amongst the writings a deed made to me, by the said M. <hi>Killigrew,</hi> of the Manor of <hi>Laur ack</hi> and Bartine of <hi>Ince</hi> in the County of <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:166866:2"/>long before the troubles began in <hi>England:</hi> which Deed was good against all claims and delinquency, and made long before the Will, so that it is evident M. <hi>Killigrew</hi> intended no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing less then to make her his heir, though to satisfie her pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing importunities he made that Will. For tis well known his affection to her was much faln of what it had been, for reasons best known to himself. Which she perceiving, and that she was frustrated in her expectation, resolves to deceive him in his intention; and so goes about by all subtill and indirect ways to defraud me of the estate, to whom it was meant; And to cousen him really after his death, who had deceived her expectation in his life, and so ruin me an innocent person in the way to her revenge; who was ingaged in 1500 <hi>l.</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal money for the onely debt of the said M. <hi>Killigrew,</hi> for part of which debt I lie now in prison.</p>
            <p>But the Parliament seizing the estate of the said M. <hi>Killigrew</hi> for delinquency, the Will (being made when he was a delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent) became invalid; By which means her sales became void, which put her to a nonplus; and so casting about which way to recover her self, made choice of Sir <hi>William Killigrew,</hi> as the fittest instrument for her purpose, whom she well knew to have as much power and as many frequent opportunities with me, as one man could have with another; (we both lodging in a house together, and seldome out of one anothers company) and he to make good her clamorous rayles upon the said M. <hi>Killigrew</hi> after his death, who in his life durst not utter a word of contumely against him; accusing him of a cheat of 3 or 4000 <hi>l.</hi> in the sale of his Manor of <hi>Kirton,</hi> in <hi>Devon;</hi> when he himself made choice of him for that purpose, and never was accompt more exactly given up, being control'd by <hi>Robert Long</hi> Esq; one of the overseers of his fathers Will; and as able an accomptant as was in <hi>England.</hi> These blemishes, and many more they cast upon this poor Gentleman in his grave, and to discredit and discountenance me that was to enjoy the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166866:2"/>estate, they gave out that I was a poor indigent worthless fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, Case in my brain and in deed rendred me to all those that did not know me, no better then a mad man.</p>
            <p>And further, that the said M. <hi>Killigrew</hi> had so blinded and incumbred his estate, as none knew how to set it right, when he good man, left it in good order for payment of his debts, of which I can witness how great his care was to have them satisfied, and transferred the care upon me in case he should die, of whom he had very sufficient experience in the payment of sir <hi>Robert Killigrews</hi> debts and legacies amounting to 27000 <hi>l.</hi> These reproaches being cast upon M. <hi>Killigrew</hi> and me, she thought would set off her virtues with the greater lustre, and so procure favour and indulgence of some of the old Parliament, whom sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> had gotten to be of her party, with purpose to over-power me. Which men she often feasted with costly entertainments, as also her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell whom sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> by his care and diligence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for her, men able to manage a business of this nature; and so all the incumbrances and disjoyntings that could be done upon this estate, was devised and put in practice by them and their agents, after the decease of the said M. <hi>Killigrew;</hi> to hold me in such a mist as they think and hope I shall never cleer up, and thus they begin their Matachine.</p>
            <p>The first thing they desired of me was, to come before a Committee to affirm or attest a Deed sealed and signed by M. <hi>Killigrew</hi> and my self, that it was my hand and seal, which accordingly I did. This Deed was to make over to sir <hi>William</hi> and sir <hi>John Berkeley</hi> (brothers to the said Mistresse <hi>Jane Berkeley</hi>) 200 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> during the life of the said Mistresse <hi>Jane Berkeley,</hi> to whose use it was made, for the payment of which Annuity there was tyed the Fee Farm rent of <hi>Laurack</hi> of 60 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> the Bartine of <hi>Ince,</hi> a Mill <hi>&amp; alia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this was done, they both told me that the said M. <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligrew</hi> had made over a trust to me, which they believed I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166866:3"/>would reconvey to Mistresse <hi>Berkeley</hi> when she should require it: But finding me slow to give answer to that, they let it slac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a while, and did not presse it any further, lest I should su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect some practice upon me, yet now and then sir <hi>William</hi> would put me in minde of it.</p>
            <p>Mean time, I chanced to come into a room where one M. <hi>Thomas Kendall</hi> and M. <hi>Edward Nosworthy</hi> were drinking together, and speaking to M. <hi>Kendall</hi> with whom I had busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, he called me by my name, whereat M. <hi>Nosworthy</hi> asked, whether I were that M. <hi>Ligon</hi> that was acquainted with sir <hi>Henry Killigrew,</hi> (who was then become a Knight) he answered that I was the same man; with that M. <hi>Nosworthy</hi> turned him about, and addrest him to me, and asked whether I did not know what sir <hi>Henry Killigrew</hi> had done for me, I desired him to tell what it was: with that he spoke very earnestly to me, and said that he had made over all his whole estate to me; I desired him to tell me some particulars, and where, or in whose hands, the deeds were, by which I might claim the estate so made over to me: and as <hi>Nosworthy</hi> had opened his mouth, with a fixt countenance upon me, to tell the whole matter, M. <hi>Kendall</hi> that knew well Mistresse <hi>Berkeleys</hi> intent was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud me of the state, gave him a private interruption, and upon that he made a sudden stop, changed his countenance, took in his voice, and spoke not a word more, and so they remained both out of countenance, by which I perceived a self-guiltiness in M. <hi>Kendall,</hi> and so after a little stay I took leave and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
            <p>After this sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> came to me, and shewed me a letter from his cousen <hi>Jane Berkeley</hi> to him, to entreat a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of me, which was to make over a trust made to me by sir <hi>Henry Killigrew</hi> in his life time; I promised to go and speak with her when he pleased: and so when sir <hi>William</hi> appointed me, I went with him to her lodging at <hi>westminster,</hi> where she spake to me to that purpose; But I gave her a flat denial, for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166866:3"/>these reasons, that I was ingaged in 1500 <hi>l.</hi> principall money, for the onely debt of the said sir <hi>Henry Killigrew,</hi> and I told her that I did assure my self that the said sir <hi>Henry Killigrew</hi> had made over his estate to me for satisfaction of those debts, and formy indempnity, and till these were discharged, I had no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to make over any trust. Whereupon she grew angry, &amp; said that if she had known my minde sooner, she would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled me in Chancery. To which I replied, that if she could compell me in Chancery, I must in obedience to that power do what they commanded, but till then I would not do it.</p>
            <p>In this angry fit I left her, and came away with sir <hi>William Killigrew,</hi> who as we returned homeward to the <hi>Savoy</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended much my temper and calmeness, that could endure such language as she gave me without returning an angry word. And as we past along, sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> asked whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were not better for me to make over this trust, (provided his cousen <hi>Berkeley</hi> would pay one pressing debt of 300 <hi>l.</hi>) then standing out, to be lyable to the whole debt, and that he as a friend advised me to do it: upon which speech of his, we made a stop, (under one of the Arches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>White-Hall</hi> and <hi>Westminster</hi>) and turned about towards <hi>Westminster</hi> again. But before we had gone many steps, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered that if that debt were discharged, others would come in their turns, which were as just and fit to be paid as that, and that it was unjust in me to slight them, though the other were more pressing at present. And so fac'd about again toward the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and from that time Mistresse <hi>Berkeley</hi> and I kept a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</p>
            <p>Not long after this, I met with M. <hi>Nosworthy,</hi> (who was now come to be of Mistresse <hi>Berkeleys</hi> party, and had bought part of the Manor of her at very easie rates) in the company of one Mistresse <hi>Yarner,</hi> who had business with him about a Statute of 500 <hi>l.</hi> upon the Manor of <hi>Laurack,</hi> whom Mistresse <hi>Berkeley</hi> referred to this <hi>Nosworthy;</hi> In whose pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166866:4"/>
               <hi>Nosworthy</hi> began to slight my claim to sir <hi>Henry Killi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grews</hi> estate, at which I put him in mind of what he said in the presence of M. <hi>Kendall,</hi> whereat he softly replyed, you must not mention that.</p>
            <p>About this time and long before, sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> and I lodged together in his mothers (my Lady <hi>Staffords</hi>) house in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> where he had all opportunities with me to work his ends, for his cousen <hi>Berkeley,</hi> and himself; for tis evident that his share weng along in the adventure, and if they could by joining together, defeate me of this estate, they would divide it between them, for without sir <hi>William Killigrews</hi> help, she was hopeless to prevail, and by his assistance, almost assured; He having a prevalent power, and command over me, and all opportunities to work his ends, knowing my poverty to be such as he needed no other security, and he at that time owing me 52 <hi>l.</hi> would not pay any part of it, lest I should commence a suit in Chancery against his beloved cousen <hi>Berkeley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I observed him in all his conversation with me, exceeding wary how he let fall the least word that toucht upon his cousen <hi>Berkeleys</hi> business, for fear I should take any hint from that, to come to the knowledge of any thing she was then put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in act; And very inquisitive to know any thing of my intention, which way I would proceed against her; and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me once say that if I had money I would exhibite a Bill in Chancery to compell her to bring forth the Deed, which she called a Trust: But finding that I had such an intention, would not pay me any part of my 52 <hi>l.</hi> though it were a crying debt, and had been long due; but still counterfeited want of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, though I saw him wastfully spend and trifle away great sums of money in useless things.</p>
            <p>In this low and necessitous condition I remained in my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Staffords</hi> house, for divers moneths: about the middle of <hi>August</hi> 1652. my Lady <hi>Stafford</hi> being then at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given order for breaking up house-keeping at the <hi>Savoy,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:166866:4"/>I was then exposed to an uncertain condition for my diet, being utterly unprovided of money.</p>
            <p>This necessitous time, sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> takes to tempt me in, and in as smooth language as he could utter, told me that his cousen <hi>Jane Berkeley</hi> was sorry that there was such di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance between us, and that he found her willing to a friendly agreement, and to right all differences that had formerly past, if I were willing to it, and that she was now going a pleasant journey into the Countrey, to see her new purchst estate in <hi>Hamp-shire,</hi> and from thence into <hi>Wilt-shire</hi> to Mistesse <hi>Ayliffs</hi> house; there to remain, till the Terme. And Mistresse <hi>Ayliffe</hi> was to begin the journey with them, who was then in <hi>London,</hi> And three or four days after this overture, Mistresse <hi>Ayliffe</hi> came to sir <hi>William Killigrews</hi> lodging, where I was invited by sir <hi>William,</hi> And upon our first acquaintance, I found her very complay sant and friendly to me, which was the first motive that induc't me to hearken to this journey; but for all this, gave sir <hi>William</hi> a flat denial; for I did assure my self, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the journey was to betray me to some great mischief. Which they had formerly tried in a rigid way, but finding that to fail, were now resolved to make the experiment in a smoother: but all this could not prevail with me, to give my consent to go this journey; whereupon sir <hi>Williams</hi> came on and gave me a second temptation, telling me that Mistresse <hi>Ayliffe</hi> was a widow of a plentifull fortune, living alone and would be glad of one for a companion, upon whom there might be no scandall, and that I being an old man, not likely to give any, she would sooner admit of me then any other; by reason our dispositions sorted so well together upon our first acquaintance; our humors being much inclined to Musique, painting, and such like arts, we should be the better company to one another: all this did not move me to give my assent to go the journey, but still held out, assuring my self, that though these pleasures were strewed in my way, yet there was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166866:5"/>a snare laid for me to fall into, and therefore gave him a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right denial: whereupon he seemed much troubled and vext, that his smooth language could work no further upon me, and therefore tried a rougher way, and as he thought would concern me nearer; and wisht me not to persist in so froward and perverse a humor, which he doubted would shortly render me ridiculous to all companies, if it were known that I slight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed such offers as these, especially coming from my best friends, and in time when I wanted bread.</p>
            <p>These hard pressures, having so much truth in them as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned my poverty, caused me to give some ear to what he so vehemently perswaded, and knowing that it was in mine own power to deny any thing they could offer concerning making over the trust, I began a little to incline to the motion, which his accustomed power of perswading and prevailing had often and frequently led me on formerly; I seemed to give my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent; but told him in how unsuitable a condition I was to wait on Ladies, that had not a peny in my purse, and that I had paid 20 <hi>s.</hi> aforhand for my lodging for a quarters rent, which would be lost if I went this journey. Whereupon he told me that I should not need to take care for any money, for my charge should be born, and for the 20 <hi>s.</hi> I should have it of him, and so delivered me presently 20 <hi>s.</hi> and the next day brought me five pounds from his cousen <hi>Berkeley,</hi> to fit me out for the journey; (but at my return to <hi>London,</hi> and that the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness was done for which he betrayed me out of Town) he took away the 20 <hi>s.</hi> by way of discompt, and did his endevour to take away the five pound, by the like discompt with his cousen <hi>Berkeley</hi> in the price of a Picture which was agreed on before we went the journey, though she had received thanks for it as a gratuity.</p>
            <p>After this, Mistresse <hi>Ayliffe</hi> came again to sir <hi>William Killi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grews</hi> lodging, and upon our second meeting, made good what sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> had promised touching my living with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166866:5"/>her, upon which I resolved to go the journey, assuring my self that without my own consent, they could work none of their ends upon me.</p>
            <p>When we had past a fortnight in the journey, and I heard no word of making over the trust, I thought I would offer somewhat to them, to try how they would resent it; and told Sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> in private, that when he saw it conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, to let his cousen <hi>Barkeley</hi> know, that I was very willing to do her any lawfull accommodation in the business between us, provided that I might do it safely, without injuring the credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or my self; and whereas she had two worthy gentlemen of her counsell, Sir <hi>George Parry</hi> for the Civill Law, and M. <hi>Merifeild</hi> for the Common Law, men of whom I had a strong confidence, would do nothing contrary to Law or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, I desired if she pleased, when we came to <hi>London,</hi> that the deeds might be put into their hands, and what they thought in honour, and honesty fit to do, I would be bound up by their Act.</p>
            <p>When I had acquainted Sir <hi>William</hi> with this, and wisht him to communicate it to his cousen <hi>Berkeley</hi> when he thought fit, there came a letter from <hi>London,</hi> which gave them to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that Master <hi>Parsons</hi> a Counsellor, and a man upon whom Mistress <hi>Berkeley</hi> much relied, both for counsell and craft in her business, which required both in a high measure, in whose hands at that time were many of her writings, they were both (contrary to their expectation) hurried towards <hi>London,</hi> who meant not to have parted with me, till the time had been elapst, for which they carried me out of Town, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time in which I was to put in my claim to the estate that was Sir <hi>Henry Killigrewes,</hi>) of which Act of Parliament, I was then utterly ignorant; and so they left me behinde with Mistress <hi>Ayliffe,</hi> at her house in <hi>Wiltshire,</hi> where I stayed five dayes, and from thence went into <hi>Somersetshire</hi> to see some friends, where I stayed till the end of <hi>October;</hi> and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166866:6"/>letters from Sir <hi>William Killigrew,</hi> to keep me at Sir <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Berkeleys</hi> where I was, for there was no business for me at <hi>London,</hi> but the truth was, he feared I should make my return to <hi>London</hi> before the time limited in the Act was expired.</p>
            <p>About the end of <hi>October</hi> I returned to <hi>London,</hi> and the next day after I went to Mistress <hi>Berkeley,</hi> to know her pleasure concerning the proposall I made to Sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> in the journey, whereupon she seemed well pleased, and desired me to invite Sir <hi>George Parry,</hi> and M. <hi>Merifeild</hi> to come and dine with her at her lodgings at <hi>westminster:</hi> which according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I did; and when dinner was ended, I expected the writings to be shewed to these Gentlemen, but perceiving her not to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, I asked her what she meant to do in the businefs for which these Gentlemen were sent for; she winkt up on me, and answered, Come, come, you and I must joyn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to defeat the Parliament; and so sent away Sir <hi>George Parry,</hi> and Master <hi>Merifeild,</hi> without doing any thing at all.</p>
            <p>A little after this, Sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> told me that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Nosworthy</hi> desired to speak with me; I asked what the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness was, he answered that it was to attest a Deed which I had formerly signed and sealed to Mistress <hi>Berkeleys</hi> use, for 200 <hi>l. per annum</hi> during her life, and that I was to do it before the Committee of Obstructions at <hi>Worcester</hi> house.</p>
            <p>I told him that I had once already been before a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee at the instance of Mistress <hi>Berkeley,</hi> to attest a Deed to the same purpose, and desired to know why it was to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; he told me that Master <hi>Nosworthy</hi> would give me the reason when I came to him. The next day Sir <hi>William</hi> sent me a note from <hi>Nosworthy,</hi> which appointed me to come to him at his lodging at an houre prefixt; which accordingly I did, but found him not within; so I was appointed to come the day following.</p>
            <p>I knew very well that <hi>Nosworthy</hi> sought all advantages to undermine me in the carriage of this business; and therefore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166866:6"/>thought good not to go alone, but brought along with me one Master <hi>Jepson Towers,</hi> Clerk of the Warrants to my Lord chief Justice <hi>Rolls,</hi> who had often importuned Mistress <hi>Berke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> and me for a debt of 300 <hi>l.</hi> due to a friend of his from Sir <hi>Henry Killigrew</hi> for which I was bound; but Mistress <hi>Berkeley</hi> as she had made her self owner of the estate, was lyable in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science to pay the debt, the Creditor being a very poor widow, ready to starve. This Master <hi>Towers</hi> I perceived to have a suspicion, that Mistress <hi>Berkeley</hi> and I, were combin'd together, to defraud poor Creditors of their just debts, and I thought I could not give him a better assurance of my integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then to call him to this meeting, partly to give his advice in the business (which I was totally ignorant of) as also to be a witness of what <hi>Nosworthy</hi> would have me to do.</p>
            <p>When we came into his lodging, we found a young man in his company, which seemed to be a sollicitor in the business by the manner of his speech, both then and afterward as shall appear; <hi>Nosworthy</hi> then addressing him to me, told me that the cause of his sending for me was, to go with him to <hi>Worcester</hi> house, to attest a Deed made to Mistress <hi>Jane Berkeley,</hi> by one Master <hi>Roberts</hi> and my self; I desired him to shew it me, which he presently did; and as soon as I had hold of it, I called Master <hi>Towers</hi> to me, (who till then stood aloof as a stranger to the business,) and we both lookt upon it, with more curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity then Master <hi>Nosworthy</hi> was desious we should, as we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by his countenance and manner of speech.</p>
            <p>But I little heeded to what he did or said, but looked ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly upon the Deed, which seemed old, rather by some art used to it, then by time or long keeping; the seal defac't so as no impression to be seen, the hand differing from mine, and not written with that freeness that originals have; rather like a Copy then an Originall, but indifferently well counterfeited, which is a very easie thing to do, for a good penman. <hi>Nos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy</hi> being much troubled at our strict perusall of the Deed,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166866:7"/>grew impatient and loud in his language, and told me that I was blockish, and doltish, and that I foold my self, to think that Sir <hi>Henry Killigrew</hi> made over his estate to me any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then in trust, and that it was a Trust, and no reall Deed to my use; and if I had a reall interest, I had lost it for not put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in my claim in time; and that I suffered my self to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of Town, to go a fine journey with Ladies, when I should have attended my business in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet there was a help left for me, if I would seal to such a Deed as he would contrive for me, which I slighted, and so Master <hi>Towers</hi> and I came away, leaving him to chafe himself in his own lodging, and as we came toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I told Master <hi>Towers,</hi> that I was confident the Deed was counterfeited, for the reasons I have named; and when we parted with him, he gave us leave to depart, without desiring me to attest the Deed, which was the onely business I was sent for; which argued a self-guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in him, that the Deed was not right. Besides, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Roberts</hi> was a man that I never had seen, and to be joyned with a man in such a conveyance that I had no acquaintance with, seem'd to me impossible. And Master <hi>Towers</hi> when he had considered, and weighed the strange extravagant and causeless distempers of the man, became a little doubtfull. But when next I saw Sir <hi>William Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligrew,</hi> I found him very much troubled that I brought <hi>Towers</hi> to be a witness of this passage, and told me that his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen <hi>Jane Berkeley</hi> wondred that I would bring a Creditor to be a witness of any passages between us; and I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived they were both sufficiently troubled and vext that I had a witness of any business that-had past between us, which till that time they were very carefull to have me alone in all their business with me.</p>
            <p>A day or two after this I went in the morning early, hoping to finde <hi>Nosworthy</hi> alone, with intention to call
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166866:7"/>him to account for the rude language he had given me, and finding him within, told him my business was for satisfaction, for the uncivill deportment he used to me at my last being at his lodging, and that I came there provided with a sword to call him out; but the name of a sword caused him to fall to so flat an humbleness, as I was ashamed to see him, and denied that he gave me any uncivill language at all, and called the Clerk to witness, who was there at our former meeting, who being in the same fear, became of the same minde, and so in stead of giving other satisfaction then with hats off, and low cringes, beg'd that I would seal to 2 Deed which they had there ready for me; but that put me clean out of patience, and so in as rude a manner as I could, came out of the room, both them following me to the stayre foot, with their hats in their hands, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that I would stay and drink, and seeing they could not prevaile with me, <hi>Nosworthy</hi> sneakt away, but the other followed me in the street ten houses off, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading me to go back and seal this Deed, by which I might recover somewhat that I had lost for not put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in my claime, but I that knew well it was but a trap to catch me, refused to do it.</p>
            <p>Another circumstance is, that Sir <hi>Henry Killigrew</hi> being a religious and conscionable Gentleman, and ever carefull of paying his debts, should not mention his debts in his Will, nor once use my name whom he knew well stood ingaged with him for fifteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound principall money, for which I have Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-bonds to shew.</p>
            <p>Another circumstance and a strong one is, that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress <hi>Berkeley</hi> coming before the Committee of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions to claime 200 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> by a pretended
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166866:8"/>Deed from one Master <hi>Roberts</hi> and my self, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that by the examination of certain witnesses the said Committee had proved that the said Master <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> had no right unto any part of the estate that was the said <hi>Henry Killigrews:</hi> She then relyed onely upon my hand and seal, and pleaded that the said estate was made to me in trust by the said <hi>Henry Killigrew;</hi> So then the Committee asked where that <hi>Ligon</hi> was, and why he came not in to make good his claime; But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then she would bring me in, or produce, or prove that trust, (being required thereunto by the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee,) she would lose her 200 <hi>l.</hi> a yeer; which she hath accordingly done, but hath caused divers other claimes to be put in, unto the said estate, and allowed by the said Committee.</p>
            <p>If the estate had been left to Mistress <hi>Berkeley</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the troubles in <hi>England,</hi> why did she not shew her Deed, and put in her claim, according to the Act? Or why does she not answer to my Bill in Chancery, and bring in the Deeds, by which her title may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, but has suffered her self to be sued to a Writ of Rebellion?</p>
            <p>Another circumstance is, that Mistress <hi>Berkeley</hi> being a Gentlewoman born of a noble family, of a great wit, and a high spirit, and one that knew well her own worth, pretending to a fortune of 20000 <hi>l.</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; why she should marry <hi>John Davis,</hi> a widower, a man in years, a father of many children, and a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner, unless it were to bring her out of those Intrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Mazes she had run her self, by his power with the old Parliament; and so cunningly they contrived this plot, (as I have heard) to have the greatest part of the Manor of <hi>Laurack</hi> claimed away by <hi>Roberts</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166866:8"/>others, that so little a part might remain to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as might be fit for Master <hi>Davis</hi> to begge, as a reward for his service in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and they had brought their plot so well onward, as of a Manor ever valued at sixteen thousand pound, there remaines now to the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> but the value of three thousand pound, and no man will purchase it at that rate. And when Master <hi>Davis</hi> had begged this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the Parliament, the claimes made by <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> and others should have reverted to him again, and that which his wife had sold in the beginning, and what he had begged in the end, should bring in the middle, which was concealed under fraudulent claimes, and the poor Creditors starved for want of bread, and I to whom the estate was made, lye and rot in prison for the debt of Sir <hi>Henry Killigrew.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:166866:9"/>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:166866:9"/>
            <head>Circumstances concerning M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
               <hi>Ayliffe,</hi> to prove this combination and fraud between S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>William Killigrew</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
               <hi>Jane Berkeley,</hi> in cheating me of an estate left unto me by S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Henry Killigrew</hi> for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his debts, for which I now lye in prison.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen Sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> perceived that neither his sweet nor sowre perswasions could prevaile with me to go the journey, Mistress <hi>Ayliffe</hi> came again to his lodging, and upon our second meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, made good what Sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> had promised concerning my living with her, which was the main loadstone that drew me on to go this journey, for upon so small acquaintance I never loved any woman more; and so being all agreed, we took Coach the next day and went on our journey; and in our passage, I thought it was my part to speak such language to Mistress <hi>Ayliffe,</hi> as would best please her eares, and deliver my self a person fit for her conversation, that I might be the more acceptable to her.</p>
            <p>Being at last arrived at Mistress <hi>Berkeleys</hi> house called <hi>East-How,</hi> which she purchast with mine, and the poor Creditors money, I was not forbidden any opportunities to testifie my service, and high affection to Mistress <hi>Ayliffe,</hi> which I could not diffemble coming really from my heart; and a time we took to walk out together into the fields, where finding a convenient feat to rest us on, we sat down and fell into a seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166866:10"/>discourse of Marriage, and the happiness of that life, and it was her pleasure to speak this freely to me, that if she were to marry, she would rather choose a man of my age, then a younger; for that she found old men less subject to change, abler to give counsell; and in their loves were permanent and constant: I askt her then, if I found all these virtues which she so much commended in my self, why I might not make my addresses to her in that way; she told me that if my fortune were answerable to my person, there was no man she would choose before me: With that I told her 'twas true that I was at present under a cloud, my estate being taken from me by a Riot, but I doubted not, but it would shortly be resetled by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then it would be as good if not better then hers: which she seemed to be well satisfied in, having formerly been told both of the one and of the other, whereat she went on and said, that if I would settle that fortune upon her and her heires, she would marry me. I gave her my faithfull promise I would do it; with that she gave me her hand, and said, Upon that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, I do here promise to marry you, our hands and hearts being joyned together. By this time Sir <hi>William Killigrew,</hi> who was at the distance of sight, was now come so neer as to hear us speak one to another, and then I told him that he was come in good time, to be witness to a contract, which had now past between Mistress <hi>Ayliffe</hi> and me, and so desired her before him to say what had past between us; she said that she had promised to marry me, upon condition I would settle my estate in <hi>Lincolne</hi> shire upon her and her heires, which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised I would do, when she pleased; and so she pulled off her glove, and gave me her bare hand again, and before his face, and in his hearing, said the same words, to which I gave the same answer; and so the contract was performed the second time, and Sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> said, he must witness this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract whensoever he was called: &amp; so we walkt home together and staid the remainder of the day, onely Mistress <hi>Ayliffe</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166866:10"/>I had some time of privacy together, to talk further of the business, which gave me a firmer confirmation of her unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable affection to me. In the evening Sir <hi>William</hi> took occasion to talk with me about this business, and asked me whether this passage between Mistress <hi>Ayliffe</hi> and me were in jest or earnest; I answered him that nothing could be more in earnest, for I had since we last parted, so strong a confirmation of her faith and affection as nothing could be more binding: this I delivered to him as a secret to a bosome friend, which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed to his cousen <hi>Berkeley</hi> after supper, but in the evening, Candles being lighted, we were all four in the Parler together, where Mistress <hi>Ayliffe</hi> began to thrust forth some words of high affection to me; whereat Mistress <hi>Berkeley</hi> took exception, and askt her what she meant to be so much in earnest; with that Mistress <hi>Ayliffe</hi> replied in these words, Have you ever seen me do this to any man before if not, you may be sure tis in earnest: this was a little before supper, Mistress <hi>Berkeley</hi> all this time knowing nothing of the former passages.</p>
            <p>Next morning Sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> took me aside, and told me that I was certainly mistaken, to think that the contract between Mistress <hi>Ayliffe</hi> and me was in earnest, for I should perceive by her demeanure towards me, when we came toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that I was much deceived, and wisht me not to use such familiarities to her as formerly I had done, for they were things she would not suffer. When I perceived this abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable treachery in him, and that he and his cousen <hi>Berkeley</hi> had an intention to ruine me in the opinion of Mistress <hi>Ayliffe,</hi> I hasted to speak with her, to see what kind of face she would put on to receive me; and when I came into her presence, found her so changed in her countenance, as I did not think one night could have made such an alteration; by which I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived how ill a night she had, and how sharply she had been reproved for setting her affection upon so odious a person as no doubt they made me appear to be: which grieved me ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166866:11"/>to see the sweet Lady, whose disposition was full of mirth and jollity, to sit now in so melancholick a posture, as hardly to afford a word; and as we were sitting together, one gazing upon another, Sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> comes in, and there foames out a speech to this purpose, glancing upon my unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiness, that being trusted in their company with a person of quality, and their friend, should be so treacherous as to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to gain the affection of a person much too worthy for me: which speech of his (had not the remembrance of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Grandfather whom I highly honoured, come fresh into my memory) had caus'd me to have done some sudden act of violence upon him, so treacherous and so false did this Monster appear before me.</p>
            <p>What language these two persons used to reproach and poyson me in the opinion of Mistress <hi>Ayliffe,</hi> may easily be guess't, for Sir <hi>William</hi> told me the next day, that she told him, she loathed me above all men. But I saw plainly the power they had over this poor Lady, and therefore thought good not to press the business any further; for what affection soever I could perswade, they would instantly destroy, and so the sweet Lady sawed in pieces between us, whose quiet and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py enjoyment of her self I valued above my own life, and so I thought fit to let the business cool for a while, till a more convenient opportunity should happen. Four or five dayes did Mistress <hi>Ayliffe</hi> retain her severe countenance, but at last seeing me carry my self in so equall and indifferent a way, as I seemed to do, she cleered up her countenance again and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came good company. But Mistress <hi>Berkeley</hi> with a scornfull look like jest, was pleased to tell me in earnest, that I deceived my self, to aime at such great heights as these, my part being to see good sauce made, and the meat well drest in the Kitchin: these fromps and scoffs I was compelled to bear, having no meanes to free my self of their company.</p>
            <p>Some dayes more we past at <hi>East-How,</hi> and then to <hi>Green-ham</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:166866:11"/>to Mistress <hi>Ayliffes</hi> house, where after three or four dayes stay, the newes came of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Parsons</hi> his death, which caused them to hast for <hi>London,</hi> with a double passion, sorrow and fear, sorrow for the losse of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Parsons,</hi> who was the main frost naile in their slippery business, and fear to leave me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde alone with Mistress <hi>Ayliffe,</hi> lest I should replant that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in her, which they had blasted with their breaths; but so much they had changed the soyle where my affections grew, as with the best manurings and husbandry of service and language, I could use, I found little or no fruit to spring up of that kinde which I thought I had planted deeply in her heart. Yet no civilities were wanting, but so mixt with strangeness, as the one seemed but to procure pardon for the other.</p>
            <p>The next day after the disturbers of our peace were depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I perceived the table in the Parler to be thrust up to one corner of the room, and another brought in, of three yards long, but very narrow, which being covered a little before dinner time with a linen cloth, there was laid at the upper end, a trencher and a napkin, and a while after, another at the lower end, and when meat was set on the table, she sate down, and pointed me to the lower end: where with as much respect as she seemed to look for, I sate down, being then three full yards asunder, and the better to keep us at a distance, her Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman had a stool plac't in the middle between us, of one side of the table, who seemed to be the stickler between my humility and her scorn; yet at other times she would let fall some favours upon me, that became her first professions. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this fire and frost, I linger'd out four dayes, and then took my leave, and went into <hi>Somerset-shire,</hi> where I remained with some good friends till the end of <hi>October.</hi> And when I came to <hi>London,</hi> went to see Mistress <hi>Berkeley,</hi> who told me she had an intent to go and keep her Christmas with Mistress <hi>Ayliffe;</hi> to whom jestingly I said, I hope you will ask me leave first.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:166866:12"/>
            <p> Whereat she took a little check, and askt whether I durst fight with a yong man that pretended an earlier interest in my Mistress then I; but I gave her an answer fit for such a questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and after a while took my leave, and a little after was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rested, and cast in prison for a debt of his, whose fortune she enjoyed, and considered neither his debts, nor my imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but took her pleasure in all. But between Mistress <hi>Ayliffe</hi> and me, there past many kinde Letters, and some of them intercepted by them or their Agents, which begat new jealousies. So that Sir <hi>William Killigrew</hi> came to me in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and told me that Captain <hi>Berkeley</hi> meant to fight with me, for making love to Mistress <hi>Ayliffe.</hi> This I knew to be a meer fab, to try whether I could be awed by these threats. But I that knew Captain <hi>Berkeley</hi> to be my friend, and no such word to come from him, slighted the others fraud, as a thing inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to his nature; and as he was a cunning subtill man, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing sorted better to his purpose, then to stave me off from Mistress <hi>Ayliffe;</hi> for if I gained her love, so as to take me for her husband, I should be able to appear above <hi>Hatches</hi> and call him and his cousen <hi>Berkeley</hi> to account for their most inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and unchristian dealing with me; besides, Mistress <hi>Ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe</hi> having lived long with Mistress <hi>Berkeley,</hi> and being able to say much of the practises and passages between them and their agents concerning the carriage of this business against me, could not but lay them open in all their base designes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair me in the wrongs I had so long suffered. This was in the time when M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
               <hi>Berkeleys</hi> Feasts, and her now husband M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis</hi> his interests could carry any thing with the old Parliament, but the tide being now turned, and a new power set up, who I hope intend nothing more then by their just proceedings to relieve the oppressed, and punish the cruelties, frauds, and tyrannies of the oppressour, they found themselves deserted of their succours, and therefore must practise some new stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem upon me, whom they conceive to be so broken and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:166866:12"/>with want and imprisonment, as hardly to lift my self up to discern their ayery practises, which they intended to put in act upon me, and so the same hook that had formerly taken me, should be cast in with the same bait to tempt me. And in <hi>August</hi> last, M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
               <hi>Ayliffe</hi> came to town, and so consequently to the prison to visit me, with as great kindnesse as was possible for any woman to shew to him she loved best, and brought in her company two persons of Honour, and Captain <hi>Berkley,</hi> whom she could not but know I esteemed very much, and sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the table with this company and some others, she burst out with the highest expressions of kindnesse that was possible, and said that she was come to town to redeem me out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and to pawne body for body to fetch me out, and that she intended to carry me to her house at <hi>Greenham,</hi> there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main with her, and Captain <hi>Berkley</hi> should be a witnesse how happily she and I should live together. This being so over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, and Captain <hi>Berkley</hi> mute at the delivery, whom I had been told several wayes to be my Rival, made me presently apprehend it to be a design upon me, as shall appear by what was to follow, for M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
               <hi>Ayliffe</hi> having past that complement, had yet somewhat more to say, which was the main top of the businesse, which she intended to deliver me in private, and as I waited on her over the Park to her boat, she imparted it to me, and it was this; that she had an earnest request to me, which I must not deny her, and after a little pawse, I promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed I would deny her nothing that was in my power to grant; with that she desired that I would not prosecute M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
               <hi>Davis</hi> any further then by my Bill in Chancery, I promised that if she would give me a speedy and a home answer there, I would not; but she gives me no answer at all, and therefore I am left at liberty. If this practice would have wrought upon me, I should no doubt have been bayld out of prison, and carried down to M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
               <hi>Ayliffes</hi> house, and so to have utterly quit my businesse which I am to move before the Judges at Salters
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:166866:13"/>Hall, and slighted the Creditors whom by all means I desire to have satisfied, though with much trouble and paine to my self, and when the time had been clapst for negotiating their business, I should have been turned off, for a silly weak old man, and returned to the Prison with my debts upon me, and rendred a scorn to all good men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Rich: Lygon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>